A Finding Aid to the Galerie Darthea Speyer Records, 1953-2010, in the Archives of American Art AAA.galedars
Archives of American Art
Galerie Darthea Speyer records
1953-2010
AAA.galedars
Archives of American Art
17.2 Linear feet
The records of Galerie Darthea Speyer measure 17.2 linear feet and date from 1953 to 2010. The majority of the collection consists of artists' files containing a wide variety of materials documenting the Paris gallery's relationship with American and European artists, as well as gallery exhibitions. Also found are scattered financial records, guestbooks, documentation on the Park Hyatt Paris-Vendome art collection, exhibition announcements, posters, and additional photographs.
Galerie Darthea Speyer (Paris, France)
Provenance
Records were donated in 2010 by Emmanuelle Gelzer, owner of Galerie Darthea Speyer.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Darthea Speyer conducted by Paul Cummings, June 28, 1976.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Historical Note
Galerie Darthea Speyer was founded in 1968 by Darthea Speyer at 6, rue Jacques Callot, Paris, France. The gallery was notable for promoting American painting and sculpture in France, until it closed in 2009.
Born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, Darthea Speyer began collecting art at the age of 15. She studied art history at the Institute of Fine Arts, New York University, and in 1950 went to Paris as a cultural attaché for the United States Information Services (USIS). In 1953 she helped organize the exhibition 12 Modern American Painters and Sculptors at the Musee National D'Art Moderne, a show that initiated a change in the way Europeans viewed American Art. While working for the USIS, Speyer founded the Centre Culturel Americain where she gave many American artists their first European exhibition. She continued to work for the USIS until 1965.
Speyer opened Galerie Darthea Speyer during the May 1968 riots in Paris with an inaugural show of works by Deborah Remington. The gallery was designed by her brother, A. James Speyer, and primarily exhibited sculpture and paintings by Americans, as well as works by some European artists. Over the next 40 years Darthea Speyer remained a powerful advocate for American artists in the European market.
Scope and Content Note
The records of Galerie Darthea Speyer measure 17.2 linear feet and date from 1953 to 2010. The majority of the collection consists of artists' files containing a wide variety of materials documenting the Paris gallery's relationship with American and European artists, as well as gallery exhibitions. Also found are scattered financial records, guestbooks, documentation on the Park Hyatt Paris-Vendome art collection, exhibition announcements, posters, and additional photographs.
Artists' files are varied but may contain biographical materials, correspondence and business records, printed materials, photographs, and slides. Correspondence is with artists and others primarily concerning the exhibition or sale of the artists' work. Also filed with the correspondence are other scattered business records regarding the artists' dealing with the gallery including exhibition documents and sales records. Photographs depict artists, artwork, exhibition installations and exhibition openings at Galerie Darthea Speyer. Printed material includes exhibition announcements, catalogs, and extensive press clippings. Files for prominent American artists such as Roy De Forest, Beauford Delaney, Llyn Foulkes, Leon Golub, Sam Gilliam, Richard Luboski, Ed Paschke, Peter Saul, Deborah Remington, and others, document a long relationship between the artist and the gallery.
This collection also includes scattered financial records from 2000 to 2002. Eight gallery guestbooks, and documentation on the Park Hyatt Paris-Vendome art collection, which was organized by Darthea Speyer.
Printed material consists of posters and Galerie Darthea Speyer exhibition announcements. Included with the exhibition announcements are lists of exhibitions by year. Many of the posters advertise exhibitions organized by Darthea Speyer at the Musee National D'Art Moderne and Centre Culturel Americain, including 12 Modern American Painters and Sculptors (1953). Additional posters advertize exhibitions at Galerie Darthea Speyer and elsewhere for artists such as Leon Golub, Beauford Delaney, Ed Paschke, Peter Saul, Hugh Weiss, and several others.
Photographs include an unidentified exhibition opening, exhibition installations at Galerie Darthea Speyer, and artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Artists' Files, 1955-2010 (Boxes 1-15; 14.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Financial Records, 2000-2002 (Box 15; 6 folders)
Series 3: Guestbooks, 1997-2009 (Box 16; 8 folders)
Series 4: Park Hyatt Paris-Vendome Art Collection, circa 1980s-2009 (Box 16; 4 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1953-2008 (Boxes 16, 17, OV 19-22; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1960s-1970s (Boxes 17-18; 0.7 linear feet)
De Forest, Roy, 1930-2007; Delaney, Beauford, 1901-; Foulkes, Llyn, 1934-; Gilliam, Sam; Golub, Leon, 1922-2004; Luboski, Richard, 1934-; Musée national d'art moderne (France); Paschke, Ed; Remington, Deborah; Saul, Peter, 1934-; Speyer, Darthea; Weiss, Hugh, 1925-; Art galleries, Commercial France Paris; Photographs; Visitors' books
- Artists' Files, 1955-2010; Series 1; (Boxes 1-15; 14.8 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Artists' files are varied for each artist, but may include biographical material, correspondence, gallery business records, photographs, slides, and printed material. Biographical material may include bibliographies, resumes, and chronologies. Correspondence is with artists and others primarily concerning the exhibition or sale of the artists' work. Found with the correspondence are other scattered business records regarding the artists' dealing with the gallery, such as shipping and sales documents, planning documents for exhibitions, and price lists. Photographs, slides, and transparencies include photographs of the artists, artwork, exhibition installations and exhibition openings at Galerie Darthea Speyer. Printed material includes exhibition announcements, catalogs, and extensive press clippings about the artists.
  The gallery maintained extensive files for prominent American artists such as Roy De Forest, Beauford Delaney, Llyn Foulkes, Leon Golub, Sam Gilliam, Richard Luboski, Ed Paschke, Peter Saul, Deborah Remington, and others, often documenting a long relationship between the artist and the gallery.
  Arrangement note
  Files are arranged alphabetically by artist's name. Documents within each file are arranged in rough chronological order. The gallery kept correspondence and other business records for each artist within one set of files, and that original arrangement has been maintained.
  - Alex, Kosta, 1966-1975; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Arnold, Anne, circa 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Baum, Don, 1981-2007; (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 5-10)
  - Berlant, Tony, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Beasley, Bruce, 1970-1973; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Brown, Roger, 1970-1994; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
  - Burchman, Jerrold, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Canin, Martin, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Carlson, Cynthia, 1967-1977; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
  - Cei, Marcos, 2001; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Comby, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Day, John, 1962-1972; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-30)
  - Dean, Peter, 1971-circa 2000; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-34)
  - De Forest, Roy, 1972-2007; (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Delaney, Beauford (Box 2)
    - Biographical Documentation, circa 1992-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1969-1979; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1991-2003; (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-16)
    - Exhibition Files, "The Color Yellow: Beauford Delaney,", 2001-2003; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    - Photographs, circa 1970-1990s; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
    - Printed Material, 1960-2004; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
    - Slides and Transparencies, circa 1973-1999 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Delfino, Leonardo, 1968-2000; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
  - Delfino, Leonardo, 1968-2000; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Durand, Christiane (Box 3)
    - Exhibition Records, 1993-2005; (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 3-7)
    - Miscellaneous Documentation, circa 1991-2010 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, 1990-2007; (2 folders; includes 1 CD-R) (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
    - Printed Material, circa 1991-2010; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - Slides, circa 1990s-2005 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Transparencies, circa 1990s-2005 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Ferrer, Rafael, 1974-2001; (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 16-22)
  - Llyn, Foulkes (Box 3)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1967-2000; (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 23-27)
    - Miscellaneous Documentation, 1976-1996 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Photographs, circa 1966-2001 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Printed Material, circa 1966-2001; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Slides and Transparencies, 1973-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fromboluti, Iona, circa 1990s-2004; (3 folders; includes 3 CD-Rs) (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Fromboluti, Sideo (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1969-2003; (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 7-11)
    - Photographs, circa 1969-2003; (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
    - Printed Material, circa 1969-2000; (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 15-17)
    - Slides, circa 1969-2000 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Transparencies, circa 1969-2000 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Georges, Paul, 1988-1995; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Gilhooly, David, 1975-1986; (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 22-25)
  - Gilliam, Sam (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1970-1986; (5 folders) (Box 4, Folder 26-30)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1990-2007; (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Photographs, 1969-1983, circa 2007; (4 folders; includes 3 CD-Rs) (Box 5, Folder 4-7)
    - Price Lists, circa 1978-1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Printed Material, 1970-2007; (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
    - Slides, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Transparencies, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Golub, Leon (Box 5)
    - Biographies and Curriculum Vitae, 1970s-2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1965-1997; (12 folders) (Box 5, Folder 15-26)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1998-2005; (7 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
    - Photographs, circa 1960s-1990s; (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
    - Printed Material, 1960-2007; (7 folders) (Box 6, Folder 11-17)
    - Slides, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Transparencies, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Granet, Roseline, 1974-1997; (11 folders) (Box 6, Folder 20-30)
  - Granet, Roseline, circa 1974-2007; (8 folders; includes 1 SD Memory Card) (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
  - Green, Art, 1969-1974; (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 9-11)
  - Hill, Clinton, 1972-1981; (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
  - Hilson, Douglas, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Hosiasson, Philippe, circa 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Hull, Richard, 1989-1992 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Isham, Sheila, 1971-1980 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Kauffman, Craig, 1970-1983, 1998; (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 19-22)
  - Kothe, Fritz, 1965, 1976-1982; (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 23-26)
  - Lee, Caroline, 1958-1976; (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 27-32)
  - Locascio, Peter, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Luboski, Richard, 1962-1982; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 34-35)
  - Luboski, Richard, 1962-1982; (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
  - Madden, Anne, 1965-1979; (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 6-10)
  - Palmore, Tom, 1971-1995; (6 folders) (Box 8, Folder 11-16)
  - Paschke, Ed (Box 8)
    - Bibliographies, circa 1980s-1993 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1971-2002; (14 folders) (Box 8, Folder 18-31)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 2004-2006; (3 folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Interview Transcript, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, circa 1970s-2005; (2 folders; includes 2 CD-Rs) (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
    - Printed Material, 1970-2005; (3 folders) (Box 9, Folder 7-9)
    - Writings about Ed Paschke, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Pierluca, 1965-1979; (8 folders) (Box 9, Folder 11-18)
  - Pikoula, Vassiliki, circa 1974-1989; (8 folders) (Box 9, Folder 19-26)
  - Pikoula, Vassiliki, circa 1974-1989; (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - Poncet, Antoine, 1997-2006 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Remington, Deborah, 1965-circa 1993; (9 folders) (Box 10, Folder 5-13)
  - Rossi, Barbara, circa 1973-1989 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Saul, Peter (Box 10)
    - Biographical Material, circa 1972-2000 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1969-2007; (9 folders) (Box 10, Folder 16-24)
    - Photographs, circa 1965-1990s; (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 25-27)
    - Printed Material, 1963-2009; (6 folders) (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
    - Slides and Transparencies, circa 1963-1998 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Schwedler, William, 1967-1989; (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 8-9)
  - Segal, George, 1967-1976; (8 folders) (Box 11, Folder 10-17)
  - Serrano, Pablo, circa 1977-1982; (4 folders) (Box 11, Folder 18-21)
  - Sigg, Irmgard (Box 11)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1981-2005; (3 folders) (Box 11, Folder 22-24)
    - Photographs, 1981-1995; (4 folders) (Box 11, Folder 25-28)
    - Photographs, 1996-1999 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Price Lists and Lists of Works, 1986-2004 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Printed Material, 1981-2005; (3 folders) (Box 12, Folder 3-5)
    - Slides, 1986-2004 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Transparencies, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Sigg, Thierry, 1984-2008; (5 folders) (Box 12, Folder 8-12)
  - Speyer, Nora (Box 12)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1968-2002; (4 folders) (Box 12, Folder 13-16)
    - Photographs, 1956-circa 2001; (3 folders) (Box 12, Folder 17-19)
    - Printed Material, 1955-2001; (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 20-21)
    - Slides, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Transparencies, circa 1980s-1990s; (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 23-24)
  - Speyer, Tilly, 1973, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Stahly, Francois (Box 13)
    - Biographical Material, circa 1970s-1989 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1968-1978, 1994; (6 folders) (Box 13, Folder 2-7)
    - Photographs, 1960s-1980s; (16 folders) (Box 13, Folder 8-23)
    - Printed Material, circa 1956-1997; (4 folders) (Box 13, Folder 24-27)
    - Printed Material, circa 1960-1980s; (3 folders) (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - Slides, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Tobey, Mark, circa 1970s; (3 folders) (Box 14, Folder 5-7)
  - Ursula (Box 14)
    - Biography, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1983-2000; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 9-10)
    - Photographs, circa 1970s-1990s; (3 folders) (Box 14, Folder 11-13)
    - Printed Material, circa 1969-2000; (4 folders) (Box 14, Folder 14-17)
    - Slides and Transparencies, circa 1990s; (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 18-19)
  - Viswanadhan, Velu, 1977-2006; (8 folders) (Box 14, Folder 20-27)
  - Viswanadhan, Velu, circa 1988-2000 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Weiss, Hugh, circa 1974-1995; (4 folders) (Box 15, Folder 2-5)
  - Zapkus, Kes, circa 1973-1988; (3 folders) (Box 15, Folder 6-8)
  - Zuka (Box 15)
    - Correspondence and Business Records, 1985-1989 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Photographs, 1968-1993; (5 folders) (Box 15, Folder 10-14)
    - Printed Material, 1970-2007; (2 folders) (Box 15, Folder 15-16)
    - Slides, circa 1974-2005 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Transparencies, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 15, Folder 18)
- Financial Records, 2000-2002; Series 2; (Box 15; 6 folders)
  This series contains scattered financial records from 2000 to 2002. Included are inventories, account statements, tax records, shipping records, and correspondence regarding finances. Documents in this series are in French.
  - Financial Records, 2000-2002; (6 folders) (Box 15, Folder 19-24)
- Guestbooks, 1997-2009; Series 3; (Box 16; 8 folders)
  Found here are eight gallery guestbooks. Each book documents at least a year of exhibitions at the gallery and includes notes and signatures from visitors. Exhibition announcements are pasted within the books to indicate the opening of new exhibitions.
  Guestbooks are arranged choronologically.
  - Guestbooks, 1997-2009; (8 volumes) (Box 16, Folder 1-8)
- Park Hyatt Paris-Vendome Art Collection, circa 1980s-2009; Series 4; (Box 16; 4 folders)
  This series contains documentation of the works of art that were selected by Darthea Speyer for the Park Hyatt Paris-Vendome hotel. Found here is a contract, press releases which include lists of artists in the collection, new clippings documenting the hotel's opening, and photographs and transparencies of artwork. Documents in this series are in French.
  - "Bon de Commande", circa 2001 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases and Clippings, 2002-2009 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 2000s (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Transparencies, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, 1953-2008; Series 5; (Boxes 16, 17, OV 19-22; 0.8 linear feet)
  Printed material consists of posters and Galerie Darthea Speyer exhibition announcements. Included with the exhibition announcements are lists of exhibitions by year. Researchers should note that this set of announcements is incomplete. Additional announcements and catalogs may be found within Series 1: Artists' Files. Many of the posters advertise exhibitions organized by Darthea Speyer at the Musee National D'Art Moderne and Centre Culturel Americain, including 12 Modern American Painters and Sculptors (1953). Additional posters advertise exhibitions at Galerie Darthea Speyer and elsewhere for artists such as Leon Golub, Beauford Delaney, Ed Paschke, Peter Saul, Hugh Weiss, and several others.
  Exhibition announcements and posters for exhibitions at Musee National D'Art Moderne and Centre Culturel Americain are arranged chronologically. Additional posters are arranged alphabetically by artist.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1968-2003; (6 folders) (Box 16, Folder 13-18)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 2004-2008 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Posters, Musee National D'Art Moderne, 1953-1964 (Box OV 19)
  - Posters, Centre Culturel Americain, 1958-1963 (Box OV 20)
  - Posters, Alphabetical by Artist, A-M, 1960-2001 (Box OV 21)
  - Posters, Alphabetical by Artist, P-Z, 1960-2001 (Box OV 22)
- Photographs, circa 1960s-1970s; Series 6; (Boxes 17-18; 0.7 linear feet)
  Photographs include an unidentified exhibition opening, exhibition installations at Galerie Darthea Speyer, and numerous photographs of artwork. Also found are a few photographs of Beauford Delaney and several of his paintings. Most of the photographs of exhibition installations include handwritten annotations with the name and date of exhibition. Researchers should note that many additional photographs can be found in Series 1: Artists files.
  - Unidentified Exhibition Opening, circa 1970s (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Installations, Identified, 1968-1977; (5 folders) (Box 17, Folder 3-7)
  - Exhibition Installations, Unidentified, circa 1968-1977; (3 folders) (Box 17, Folder 8-10)
  - Beauford Delaney and Artwork, circa 1970s (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Beauford Delaney and Artwork, Negatives, circa 1972 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1960s-1970s; (3 folders) (Box 18, Folder 3-5)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Negatives, circa 1960s-1970s; (2 folders) (Box 18, Folder 6-7)